Remember back in lesson two when Katherine used a
AsyncTask hooked up to a refresh button to update
our data? Rato talked about how that was a
bad idea, because the AsyncTask is not tied to
the activity life cycle. The virtual machine will hold
on to the activity object as long as the
AsyncTask is running, even after Android has called onDestroy
for the activity and expect it to be discarded.
If you rotate your phone, the behavior is to
destroy your activity and instantiate a new one. The
naive AsyncTask implementation now has two threads trying to
perform the same update, and so forth. The point is,
it's not the best pattern for a potentially very
long background operation, such as fetching from web services. If
you leave the app, the asynctask will continue to
run for as long as your process is kept alive,
but will run at a low priority, and your process
will be the first thing to be killed if the device
needs more resources. And there's a bigger problem. Your app
has to be visible and running in the foreground to instantiate
the task in the first place. Because we started a
task, to update the weather when we started the app, this
can have undesirable behavior if the weather changes rapidly. So
now we're going to learn the right way to perform updates.
We'll want to automate the process while the app is in
the foreground. But even more importantly, we want the app to get
regular updates in the background with minimal battery drain. That will
be especially important later in this
lesson when we introduce weather notifications.